thank you very much we had a teaching
this this morning right and it's about
what the translators are doing and we
split that all the translation work up
into nine translators primary
translators because there are about nine
kinds of Buddhist language that I guess
she has to learn and so I thought for
this fundraisers luncheon I would go
through one idea from each school from
each translation these are the
translations it's about two thousand
seven hundred and sixty four pages word
and this is the work that the
translators have done in the last two
years and they are unscheduled to work
some of them are scheduled for twenty
more years the abhidharma translation is
scheduled for twenty more years and
things like that and I I just thought I
would go through the one idea from each
school from each translation and Tim was
brave enough to carry them here in a
suitcase and we'd like to donate them to
the three jewels okay and we didn't have
time to finish it this morning which is
kind of frustrating for me so I want to
finish it and then the rest of the talk
from last night is one of them so I
thought I could kill two birds with one
stone so to speak and just do the whole
thing okay I think you could spread out
a little bit is that okay is it legal
just spread out cuz make yourself more
room okay use up this space come on
yeah be more comfortable you can come up
a little bit if you want I don't know if
it's more comfortable
make sure that at least six
so I'll go through those nine or ten
ideas just because I have it in mind and
I Tim asked me to finish it sometime
which is never going to happen so I
thought I'd just do it now
and then I'll try to at the end give
some inspiring message to for the ACI
Global Summit which is happening
tomorrow okay and I'll inspire you to
carry the message to the globe and I I
asked to have this printed about 20
minutes ago which is typical and they're
coming okay
from or always bringing them okay so
you're gonna have you okay yeah you have
some where are you projecting yeah this
morning I'm gonna continue from this
morning because Tim Lauren how asked me
to is that trouble for you obviously
okay take your time and I'll just start
okay so this is a reading which you are
going to get in about 10 minutes
it's being printed as we speak and it
was the reading for the sponsors this
morning and I didn't get to finish it
and I I'm really attached to it so here
we go so we have nine main translators
we have about I don't know a hundred
secondary translators if you count China
we have we're training about 80
translators in China and the idea is
that these books will be translated into
another 35 languages or something also
Canadian it's
that girl's gonna do it it's gonna
change all the abouts to a boot and dump
like that whatever that is one day I
asked my boss and diamond company how
many grams in a kilogram and he said
it's not only in America yeah okay so
anyway I'll go I'll just start and
you're gonna get the pictures shortly
okay and I'm starting from the bottom
school and I'm working up okay so one of
these books is abhidharma
and as we talked about there was kind of
a dark ages in Buddhism from 500 BC to
287 seventh centuries are considered
sort of a dark ages and I don't know why
and it's kind of depressing to imagine
why but right after Lord Buddha passed
his teachings on emptiness were
immediately misunderstood in a much
lower version which we call the
abhidharma school and so the teachings
on emptiness just got immediately got
corrupted and and became a very
elementary and they they didn't really
work as well for seven centuries so and
and interestingly in the monastery you
don't study that school till the end of
the gésier program the last two years
you might spend some time on abhidhamma
but but my karma was that when I showed
up at the monastery my teacher was
teaching it so he taught it to me for 12
years and we translated the first time
almost commentary which is a very famous
commentary and so it's kind of dear to
my heart it is the basis of DCI so most
of DCI stuff somewhere you can find in
in the abhidharma especially that the
fourth chapter which is on karma is
accepted by all schools as being nobody
wrote a better chapter about a better
presentation
it's complete and it's accepted by
everyone so the foundation of the four
steps and all that comes from a be
dumber and here's your reading from
Orion we should thank him okay to stress
you out
he he thought he was keeping up with me
okay so the first one the translator
father Dharma is Stanley chance he's
from Shenzhen China he's an amazing
young man 28 29 something like that yeah
yeah and he's also in charge of our
China's soft power program which is
teaching very very advanced Chinese
business people these ideas and he said
he's just like kind of a Mozart Mozart
wunderkind after yeah okay London
he's abundant and the quotation I put I
put one quotation from each school and
the school the quotation from that one
is called such a supper mention them
llama topic du Chien em such a country
dinner last sanam Kentucky burger Sam
elongate Dumbarton do much in of Simeon
tendon card and ego paddy
Gopi need a Lanham comedy power very
famous opening of the a baton and we
have to memorize it in the in the
monastery it's about 150 pages or
something
so I've forgotten the rest okay but I
know and that the whole abhidharma
starts out with all things in the world
can be divided into two types one is
such a and which means has stains you
have mala and mala as I mentioned this
morning means it came into English as
malevolent and what was that Disney
character Maleficent yeah yeah so it
means bad and then if you find a person
who's extraordinarily
pure and free of that you would call
them vin mala right so that means no
more mala and so and and it's you know I
studied it for 12 years tonight and I
I'm just appreciating it now and what it
what it says is 99.99999% of all the
things in the world will cause you pain
and will hurt you okay so it's basically
abhidharma is a list of things that can
hurt you and things that can help you
and the things that can hurt you are
99.999999%
and then he divides all things in the
universe into changing and unchanging
which is the same as saying things which
have a cause and things which don't have
a cause existing things which don't have
a cause okay like space
give me some word space cessation
meaning the end of anger in the human
heart for example cannot change will
never change and emptiness itself and
yes empty space these are the famous
ones
so there's out of the whole universe
there's a there's only one changing
thing which will not hurt you and that's
the study of the Dhamma and the
understanding of emptiness it's the only
changing thing which will not hurt you
your body will hurt you your eyes will
hurt you your nose will hurt you
your friends will hurt you your in your
city will hurt you
everything will hurt you in the
abhidharma system except for what you do
it the three jewels seriously you can
say that every other activity in New
York City will hurt people so you know I
know you kind of maybe see yourselves as
a weirdos in a white room on Fifth Third
Street Fifth Third Street I figure
Street run we started like two doors
down and but
actually you are the only thing in New
York that won't hurt people it's going
on here and so you know from a from a
from a point of view of the whole
universe
and the point of view of America what's
going on in this room on a daily basis
is the only thing that won't hurt people
in New York you see so you should have a
little bit in Buddhism we call Nagi ow
you should have a little hot spot about
who you are you are very special what
you are doing here is very special and
you are the only changing thing in New
York that won't hurt people okay this is
all Biederman this is basic I'll be done
then do maintain I'm saying in the
non-canonical bunny there are three
unchanging things which will not hurt
you okay one is space and that's we're
going to talk about it maybe later if I
get there but basically the place in
which you are sitting the place you are
occupying with your body which will
still be here when you walk out and will
still be here if the planet is destroyed
when Trump blows up everything there
will still be a space here that doesn't
change and it doesn't hurt people you
say you can walk through it it's always
there and then cessation what we call
cessation one is called a social tango
and social thought minge gopis ASOS or
tango sauce or Tom minge Coppa the end
of negativity in the human heart is
permanent it will never change you see
and it has two versions okay one comes
from a lesser understanding of emptiness
and one comes from a direct
understanding of emptiness so if you
teach the pen correctly then a person
gets a lower understanding of emptiness
an intellectual understanding emptiness
and because of that understanding
certain negativities big
begin to become impossible okay and we
often do the two husbands Peter did a
famous two husbands video that went
viral in Russia or Germany or both I
don't remember and this is where we
demonstrate in a funny skit that the
husband who yells at you at home doesn't
exist and you are angry at something
which doesn't exist if you understand
that intellectually if you start the
process of being a person who cannot be
pissed off no one can do it to you if
you start to understand that the husband
who's not coming from you it's
impossible you start to you start to
travel towards Nirvana which is the end
of anger for example so and it doesn't
happen the first time you hear the pen
you know then you don't it doesn't
happen that you go home and your husband
yells at you and you're like I know
you're coming from me honey everything's
cool it takes time but in time in
intellectual understanding of emptiness
which means that your husband's not
coming from himself
okay that's empty double negative is
emptiness without the double negative
it's dependent origination he's coming
from you there are flip sides of the
same coin
okay so he's coming from what you did in
the past you yelled at someone at your
job and tonight your husband's yelling
at you if you really understand that pen
thing you will get less and less angry
each time okay it doesn't work the first
night trust me don't feel depressed if
you forget okay but in abhidhamma terms
that's called social tom minge gopis
also talk men means it does not depend
on the direct perception of emptiness it
can be produced by an intellectual
understanding of emptiness okay then the
final thing in abhidharma score which is
which won't hurt you which is unchanging
is social tango say so sir tango
$50 words so sore in this case what no I
feel my money I don't know when he gets
in New York he he's very expensive
incidentally he cost me like four five
hundred dollars a day really okay anyway
so sir in this case means the
individually you see the the four higher
truth before our truths mistranslated as
noble truths there it's a missed chance
it's a very bad missed transition the
word means Arya the word means there are
four things you understand when you see
emptiness directly and because of that
you can't have certain negativity in you
and you'll be start to become a Buddha
you start to reach in the money okay so
these are unchanging things and they
cannot hurt you okay and that's
basically Dharma okay I finished the
lowest score because we have to move and
and to teach a major text in each school
takes we did 72 classes in January in
two weeks and each one takes five hours
of prep six hours of prep and I mean
it's in it's intense we're doing a few
minutes on each it's cool okay second
school and the translator for second
school is Allison Cho she's also from
Shenzhen she's she became Stanley's
partner due to our intense translation
work together which is convenient for me
because they always travel together I
always I don't have to invite them
separately and she's translating one of
these books here is the ancient valve
morality vinaya okay which is considered
part of the abhidharma school and what
she's working on right now it's very
very cool
there are 306
before nuns vows full nuns vows and they
were lost a thousand years ago the
lineage was broken in in Tibet due to an
evil king who killed all the nut monks
and nuns and they it takes twelve nuns
to make a nun and he killed them until
there's 11 and so there hasn't been a
recognized lineage of full nuns in Tibet
there have been in other countries China
Thailand Burma
I guess Vietnam but we're restoring the
version of the monks vows the nuns vows
which came to Tibet so there are 18
different versions of nuns vows 18
different schools of Vinaya
and the one which came to tibet has been
broken for a thousand years and we're
rebuilding it and it's very very cool
and very exciting and so and it's
extremely difficult the literature is
very ancient
it's the oldest language of Buddhism and
the books are all corrupted they've all
been broken they've all the blocks are
smashed burned missing and we John Brady
god bless him let's get my hand
and Christina Jessica
and Bimala who Norah's helping
they've been recovering the ancient
books John's been working for thirty-one
years on it and we have enough ancient
books recovered that we are able to
piece back together the vows and it's
very very beautiful so what I had talked
about this morning with the sponsor
group the VIP group was a certain
concept that we happen to be working on
right now it's kind of mid-level vows
mid-level none spells they're defined by
serious enough to have to confess but
not serious enough to get kicked out in
the monastery for a day and and the
vowel we're working on right just like I
just took things that run them is that
you're not allowed to stand with a man
in a place where people cannot see you
both you know so you can stand with a
man out in an open field or something
like that that's okay but you can't go
behind the trees where somebody cannot
see you and and then that whole thing
relates to an ancient teaching from
abhidharma called matzah and tell you
which word is gonna translate definitely
lotta yeah okay and and that comes from
this vow teaching this particular vows
so one is where tell you is easy you
control yourself in public you don't
want you don't want people to say gosh
you Michael did this thing I saw him and
you know so you when you're in public
you are very righteous
that's called tell you and it is still a
virtue according to our be Dharma every
time you do a good karma you have both
of these going on in your mind and it's
very interesting Buddhist psychology 451
right he translated it 51 mental
functions going on at the same in the
human mind capable in the human mind
basically 51 different functions two of
them are always present if you're doing
a good karma one of them is tell you
what
to means you care about how others feel
and and that can be a good thing to like
you don't want to hurt it's not just
others impression of yourself but you
don't want to upset other people so you
try to control yourself you try to be a
good person I was reading the book nor a
friend of ours wrote a book about honor
honor killings in Pakistan and and she's
a big advocate against that and she's
talking about honor though I read the
introduction last night and the whole
thing is the sense that you don't want
to embarrass your family especially your
father and and that's honor you know and
and that's a good thing that can be a
good thing that you don't want to hurt
the people around you you want to be a
nice person because you don't want to
upset the people around you that's
called tell you it is present in all
cases of good karma somewhere in your
mind you are thinking that you don't
want to hurt the people around you okay
the other one is more subtle and it has
to do with the open walls lotsa what
that means even if you were by yourself
in your room alone and you had a chance
to do something bad which is mainly
pornography on the internet etc you can
show yourself and you avoid it because
you because of your own self what do you
call it your your self image your self
esteem how you feel about yourself and
you you know you get ready to turn on
then you're like wait this isn't what I
want to be this is not who I want to be
and you you know you can show yourself
and and that's a pure and see these two
things go together every time you do a
good karma these two thoughts are
swimming around in your mind somewhere
and that's a very very important
teaching from this second example of the
lowest school I'll be its an arbiter my
version which is vinaya which is
morality bad morality okay we finished
the first school yeah okay we're
trucking you're doing the gadget course
in one evening okay the third school
which is and but I put their pictures in
here and I got a good picture of Adam
he's really handsome I him and his wife
I don't know last summer in France and
you know and they're having a baby
pretty soon okay and he's doing a book
called you know you call it Buddhist
logic
it's called pramanas a pramana pramana
means a correct perception accurate
perception so you're on in Buddhism
you're not drunk you're not crazy you're
not overwhelmed by jealousy and you see
things that aren't there
okay like emotions or motion like you're
in a at the red light and the two cars
next you go backwards and you have a
misperception that your car is sliding
into the intersection so pramana means
you don't have any of these things
affecting your perception your
perceptions are correct okay and then
it's a whole school of Buddhism it's the
second school called South Tran pika
which means followers of Sutra okay and
and they say we don't agree with those
abhidhamma guys because they're not
following Sutra they're following a book
that was put together by 500 scholars
after Buddha died and admittedly they
messed it up which all committees do so
that's why we don't do translation by
committee frankly we pick one specialist
we train them for 10 20 years that's our
vinaya specialist or that's our citrus
south trent occur okay
so Adams doing a book called by Dharma
Cathy call perminov Arctica which means
commentary on how do you know and you're
having a correct perception you see and
and how do you when you look at a cow
how do you see a cow you're looking at
arms you're looking at legs you're
looking at horns
then how does your mind make a cow out
of these pieces and this is the big
subject of their school and he's into a
very cool subject call you ujin say you
Yuchun yo means all the possible objects
of perception and your Chen means all
the ho those by the way those are called
deja in Sanskrit and and it it came to
mean a place like Bangladesh there's
other dishes right anyway
it came to mean country or a location in
a country but it means so in Buddhism
this is very cool deja means the object
and Dacian means the State of Mind
holding the object so the object and
subject okay which already means that
the idea that when you see emptiness
directly the mind becomes the object is
wrong okay it is described as pouring
water into water but you definitely have
a state of mind going on otherwise you
couldn't be there you couldn't see
emptiness okay
so non duality water into water it
doesn't mean your mind disappears and
and the word itself for object and
subject means it has to be that way your
mind never turns off ever your mind has
gone on for countless eons billions
countless billions of years you've had a
mind and you cannot turn it off you can
take drugs you could shoot yourself in
the head no you can do anything you
cannot turn off the human mind it will
continue forever and it has been forever
okay and then he's doing this cool thing
levels of objects levels of dishes and
there's many many beautiful terms say me
nu Shen you ding dong Yi you
mooo you sure you yeah five levels of of
object okay five levels of objects so if
I'm looking at or his face handsome face
I mean it's all karma no I mean he's the
color and shape of his face he called me
Q so it means what am I looking at the
object the object I'm looking at okay
and for me right now it happens to be
also no you know you'd word for $50 that
nice though I said high tone I'll give
me a $25 okay 25 if it's not high tone
it's it's what he said the first time if
it is high tone it's what he said the
second time for half price
yeah so Lu you means right now I'm
having a direct perception of his face
you know and tomorrow on the plane to
Tokyo I will have an indirect perception
of his face okay
a memory okay so that's mu means direct
shoot means uh you know somebody says
this is already in New York and I said
yeah I saw him yesterday he wasn't
planning on going anywhere and then I
have a his face becomes an indirect
object why is it important in the study
of emptiness tired to abhidhamma $50
except worth now people come to depend
on him and what's it got to do it seeing
his face directly you're saying it's
facing directly with what I said about
abhidharma yeah nice emptiness can be a
mu you or shoe you okay
mu you means by the way I want $50 who's
Rebecca are you on it okay
she keeps record I pay extra if she
forgets somebody so sure you know you
yeah sure you means when I teach the
emptiness with the pen you have a sugar
emptiness is a
you you are understanding emptiness but
not directly you are figuring it out
okay from what I say then one day you
have a it becomes a blue you okay it
becomes a direct perception so it's a
big difference between I like to say
hugging your friend or thinking about
them when they're ten miles away you
said I mean who you is much more
satisfying then thinking about no it is
right and it's much more satisfying to
hug emptiness directly then to you know
think about how it would have been don't
ask me questions I can hardly get you
this stuff without questions okay what
wait you cannot ask a question with gum
in your mouth okay
just swallow when p'chai want to hit you
with a with a rosary I'm telling you
yeah yeah yeah yeah exactly
and there's three versions of it one is
logic you can use logic to perceive it
one is called the convention and if I
say the big black or something like that
to refer to emptiness and then based on
that you you get some concept of
emptiness that's the second way what's
the third way for $50 even word Todd in
DC I level seven okay stop prop Jack
charm yeah who'd said that damn you're
hot tonight
what's that yeah it's of three kinds of
indirect perception that can be figuring
it out yourself from guess not talking
about the pin geshe-la uses metaphors
like the big black or you know the
eternal space or something and or which
is called convention or the third option
is called Authority okay you trust the
person you don't understand why gets
less said about the pen exactly but you
just take it because you like him or you
have established that he does
like to lie in public okay like that
okay so anyway those are three when you
perceive emptiness to any of those three
methods it's called sugar indirect so so
far we have migoo which is always
praised and tonight it's a Lulu
it's a perception direct perception
phase but tomorrow will be a shoe you
when I remember or logically what I
recall where he would be something like
that and then there's in Tonga you're
said then dungee you which how do you
take his face and in the deeper studies
it's become shaneoh session you shaneoh
means a feeling I have about him which
is mistaken okay
Shan means mistaken we have some Bushido
for $50.00 not word or or this guy from
Canada sham Bushido okay cancel that one
yeah it's one of your loads on text in
was it course 14 yeah freedom from the
for attachment socio means how I feel
him to be and the implication is wrongly
wrongly I feel like he's coming this way
if he says gets a lot I was really
stupid talk tonight you know then I will
I'll get upset because I think he wanted
to say something bad about me so then I
have a shinu Shengo means I want to
think of him as coming this way okay and
you can call it zentangle you're the
same but Chanyeol is more evil okay
Shane yo means I feel like or is coming
this way okay where's the weight coming
from yeah it's coming from me okay
so when you cut the shin you you
understand or II when you stop thinking
that the pen is coming this way a
certain kind of pennis is removed from
the equation between you and the pen an
imaginary pen that you made up called
the pen which is coming from the pen
you see when you remove that one you
start seeing the real nature of the pen
you see that mean so we have all these
layers of of interpretations of Hector's
face or or his face which are false and
we build them and we never see the real
one
okay got it like that which is the MiG
you which is the one I'm really looking
at okay so this is this is school too
we're not even up into the higher
schools yet but it's sexy and you could
see why school number two the study of
logic and perception is called vaquita
emptiness unfortunately ACI 13 is the
key to emptiness and when I taught ACI
13 okay now since since I mom among
historical ACI it's kind of the theme
this weekend where has they see I've
been in whereas there's that going it
seems to be a crucial weekend
in the history of ACI but just so you
know summer I mean there will be stories
about a CIA hundred years from now
here's one for you when I taught ACI 13
I lost half my students in one night she
was there or maybe you weren't I don't
remember but you know it was I studied
logic I started the second school and
people freaked out and I was kind of
disappointed you know people fell off
like flies and so then when I finished
they say 13 the people who are in left I
said we're gonna do love something fuzzy
and warm called low John you know HDI 14
so hang in there come back next time and
then we went on to these poems about
love and I then they all came back
slowly they all came back and then
people say there's a reason why the
logic was number 13 okay
that's now you graduated from second
school okay but you get a feeling for
what's the point of the second school
it's those layers of false objects okay
which is what Adam is translating this
week
okay the next school is mine only school
and as I said this morning we made a big
mistake we wanted to cover all the
schools so we we picked the most
important book of the mind only school
which is a book by Tom Carper called
difficult points of the mind only school
Samsung back on there and it's a
okay I'm sorry you gotta say it for what
it is and we got how many pages into it
we got like three pages into and we like
junked it we said we can't do this and
I'm in a weird stage in my life I don't
know anyone who can help me I'm not
aware of anyone who can help me our
tango can help me sometimes but if I
can't figure it out I can't call anybody
there's nobody else so I'm like we need
help you know we need to find help so I
asked word to look through the
collection of ancient scripture scans
which have been worked on for over 30
years by a group called Tibetan Buddhist
Research Center and now called BD or
something
and I'm pleased that tonight we have the
direct the director the man who directed
it for many years
and because of him and his work his
dedication he just retired and we stole
him
he's just been replaced I think in the
last few months he I think he wanted to
kind of do something even more fun but
they have saved eight million thirteen
how many sixteen million pages of
ancient books and then very very kindly
without charge they have given them to
our project for I don't know 30 years so
what we type is their scans and without
them we wouldn't exist without the
typing the translation cannot happen so
we should give another
so I asked word you know go dig around
their stuff you know you don't know how
we talk about you relent
I think yeah go dig in their stuff see
if you can find some and he found a very
beautiful commentary what's the dates of
the author I forget yeah not too old
like - 150 years old and this is a lama
who explained some coppice commentary
and he did a good job so we're working
through that we're translating that and
it's very exciting master wordsmith is
there he's he's our most amazing word
remember we call him the human computer
and I'd like to get my hand for working
and I'm very apologize I didn't have a
chance to say how you're dead
I tell my apologize and I hope he didn't
freak out too much from the class like
disown you but he probably did already
okay okay so here's cool thing about
mind only and I explained it on lunch
today but you know probably forgot
already
so they say the human do you want it
Thanks are you in the mood now what I
want you to explain okay this is your
examination it's the two extra parts of
the mind and what you're translating
this last week you know so what happens
when this part of the mind figures out
that part of the mine and what what's
left of this part of mine okay go lock
loud is that okay or you want to come up
stand up here quick quick yeah I know
mind only way I knew you're okay so mind
only school so I specially explained
we're doing this text it's called the
difficult points in mind only school and
that is not a figurative name it's a
really difficult book and it goes into
some of the most technical points of
like the most technical school in
Buddhism so so the book the original
book by je tsongkhapa who's the founder
of our tradition is called in tibetan SE
e dunk when she yes there's more but
that's with that so so those are the two
extra consciousnesses in the mind only
school so usually in buddhism there's
six consciousness the five senses
Yeah right and the mind but in the mind
only school they add two extra
consciousnesses and it's super confusing
and so as if it wasn't confusing enough
Jason compa named the book he didn't
name the book the two extra
consciousnesses he named it a dong Quan
Chi E just means mind so for 600 years
people are like mind and foundation
consciousness but that has nothing to do
with the book at all as if it wasn't
hard the title is difficult okay so what
the title means is kunshi which is
foundation consciousness I'll talk about
that and this thing called Muni say noon
II okay noon is short for no more and no
long means Glacier afflicted negative
state of mind anything that disturbs
your state of mind cliche right and so
the whole book is basically divided into
two parts the type about the type the
part about Konishi and the part about
muni okay and not in that order right
right cause you know in that order not
in the order of the title okay
so we just went through a long section
on kunshi which is foundation
consciousness right that is in the mind
only school let me talk about the mind
only school for one second okay so
because it's really confusing the mind
only school is basically the school that
the Buddha taught at the end of his
career right there's three turnings of
the wheel
Hector taught course 15 right very
lovingly and in in that course they talk
about the third turning the wheel
basically when Lord Buddha first started
teaching is five disciples and so on he
taught about suffering about the heaps
about the consciousness is very like
clear stuff people okay sounds good we
like that and then you start seeing wild
stuff you say nothing exists you have no
eyes no ears no mouth no nothing and
people like that right and he threw that
on vulture
speak and the Heart Sutra and the
diamond cutter suits are some of the
most famous Buddhist texts and they're
still boggling people's minds people
don't know what these texts mean anymore
right Ashley that's what we got it all
right okay so so then this Bodhisattva
comes along he's like it's like a
Buddhist joke so boring stop it walks
into a teaching she was like Lord Buddha
she's like first you say everything's
real then you say nothing's real which
one is it right and so that's when the
mind only school was born with that
question he said some things are real
something not so real right and this is
the ancient tradition of Buddhism where
you always give a teaching to the level
of the students you don't just start
talk abouting emptiness to newbies and
they're like run out of three jewels and
you know okay so the way he explains it
so the way he explained it is he added
two extra consciousnesses one is called
cushy right and that's where all the
seeds that we collect all the Karma's
say bok choy all those are the seeds
those are the potentials in the mind and
they go into what we call the crunchy
and somehow you don't want to know how
trust me yeah you can read my book it's
gonna sell like five okay
those seeds become your experiences
that's the basic that's it they become
blue they become you know
geshe-la they become New York okay
that's enough so you don't want to know
so and then now we're in the second part
of our book which is Muni so Noonie is
they explain how how we have bad
thoughts
basically because Buddhism is also all
about suffering right pain how do we get
rid of our problems so the point is
second half of the book which we
arduously and laboriously got to is
about that okay you got it okay good so
now they're talking about actually very
important subject kestrel just talked
about
Abbey Dharma you talked about cessations
right source or tungee go yeah and so
sore tongue minge go right how do we end
our problems that's that's what it means
pretty much right okay so in the book
they're saying okay there's this thing
where all our problems are kept right
and with it or all these other problems
like not only do you have like bad
things happen to you but you know when
you do it you feel bad you think it's
bad when your mind touches it it's bad
and so on and so forth and they go into
categorizing that it's really annoying
and that's very detailed it's amazing
but it's it's okay and so they explain
all that but then they ask it's like a
trick question cuz you got to think you
got to remember this about what's the
thing with all the other schools they're
wrong yeah they're not they're not
complete they're perfect for this
student but there's another one that can
take you the whole way you can't get
enlightened with them right so the
question is if it's true that you have
this part of your mind that's broken and
it's accompanied by all these other
parts of your mind that are messed up
when you reach a stage when you seen the
ultimate like emptiness directly and
you're supposed to never have to come
back to the desire realm this place
where we just want food and sex
okay that's what that's all the first
time I'm going to find it not me don't
look at me like that
mhm Wes we reach that stage what happens
to that mental function in our mind and
to get rid of it do we need to form do
we need to have a full lobotomy or can
we just pull that crap out and then go
along and be cool in like in samsara
[Applause]
yeah when you cut the tumor out dude do
you also cut the brain out I'll be
Dharma says yes you disappear in nirvana
okay and then his school where he's at
in his translation this week because I
wanted you to feel how are exciting unis
you know we don't know how this story's
gonna end but you know they're in the
operation in the darkness
should we take out the brain or not and
then we determined it in we don't know
okay
next goal we reached the four school
which is middle middle middle way and
the middle way school has two parts okay
the middle way school has a lower middle
way and higher min the way basically you
can say there's five schools if you look
at it that way okay and the one of the
great teachings of the lower half of the
middle way is a Tsongas presentation of
The Wheel of Life Tenjin then they sing
in Nam give baiting engine on your mug
name tangent Delta Luke toodle-loo me to
not open a very famous study the lions
dance master it and you will come to see
dependent origination as its expressed
in the Wheel of Life
okay which I'm sure you're learning at
the three jewels he connects the lions
dance meditation directly to
understanding the Wheel of Life
Howdy's then there's a picture here how
do you stay in the Wheel of Life how do
you get into the Wheel of Life and this
is being translated by one of our
students from Indonesia who lives in
Singapore who's of Chinese ancestry and
his name is su Gong XI and it's a
beautiful story about su Gong I was
giving a talk in Singapore to about 1200
people and there's this and it was one
of those audiences that goes up you know
like I'm on the level of the second half
of the audience and then some of the
audience's up there and there's one
intense guy and he's like you know and I
keep looking at him there's 1200 people
and I keep looking at him you know like
then that the director of Singapore
Jenny Wang came on the stage of the
break I said go find that guy go get
that guy he's important for you
and she went got him and now he's the
director of Indonesia he has eight
cities he has 31 three jewels
equivalents in Indonesia and he's
translating these ancient books and he's
intense
he's and his wife is equally intense so
there are two intensive and so anyway
he's translating this ancient commentary
to the Wheel of Life and I show you
something we we just figured out so and
and you're kind of a Wheel of Life
expert because of his presentation
Hector's presentations are real way of
life I use it all the time how he did it
graphically was groundbreaking so you
don't appreciate him but I do so there
were there's 12 links as you know like
12 o'clock in the Wheel of Life and they
start number one as well you miss
understand the pen which means you
misunderstand your husband when he's
yelling at you
and you think he's coming this way and
only because of that misunderstanding
can you do link number 2 you call him
I almost said a bad word you call him a
bad name yeah you make fresh karma you
make karma
okay and then the wheel starts to spin
you see and it ends with death old age
and death okay and and you know we
learned the twelve links and in your
mind you feel like this okay you feel
like the trouble things goes like this
like like a Clark and I've been doing 12
links I don't know for 30 years and and
when I think of it I think of a Clark
right and then what happened in our
translation class it's like oh wow
Buddha says no no it's three wheels it's
always three wheels
the first wheel goes good and the second
wheel goes weak and the third coin goes
cut it up that's jeep jeep gone and it's
always it's always like this car moves
and that was this cog and this was this
so in this life you misunderstand your
husband you answer him when he yells at
you when you get home no I'm not stupid
you're stupid then that connects the
link number 3 of the second wheel and
then you get reborn because you have
karma and you live a whole life up to
link number 10 and then that triggers
the third wheel 11 and 12 and you're
born again and then you die again
so it's really one you can't think of it
like a clock anymore you have to think
of it as all right and imbue okay and I
want you to translate it that way then
it got deeper and he said you know and
who told me Connie I think it was so
Jacqueline Jacqueline sent today at the
table it's quite nice it's really it's
not going this way and it's not even
going this way it's going this way you
see and it's you're looking at the wheel
from above she said you started it at
lunch it was brilliant
I mean sometimes but yeah it's not crank
crank crank
it's ring ring ring and it goes and then
that the third one connects to the next
first one ring
I am right and you're just going down
keep going down and you keep crap keeps
happening because it keeps spinning one
spin two to spin three three spins one
one spins two and it's a it's a very
beautiful idea so you know you have to
figure out the graphics just maybe you
do it you do it as a clock first and
then you teach it that way and then say
you know what maybe it's like this
and you do the three graphically in a
linear fashion and then you make it
bird's-eye view and something like that
and then that would be more accurate
okay so that's what we learned last
month in in our translation we got to we
got to the technical presentation of
that great green green okay I'm just
telling you how it sighting it is to be
in the room you know in that room in
Sedona doing a translation session it's
like it's like you know everyone's
making a discovery every ten minutes or
something I mean it's cool okay
all right what's how should I do this we
need a break but what do you think
should I take a break in about 15
minutes how's that and then we come back
and I'll give you a pep talk for the
tomorrow thing okay
all right next text is by Nicola Shah
who many of you know he showed up at
Diamond Mountain when we're getting
ready for the first three year between
and I mean the second one and he just
built cabins whose cabin he built grants
cabin yeah and he just quietly came and
he just labored like that but his story
is very beautiful New York he talked
like that you want a coffee and his
story is very it's to me it's very
beautiful he was a hippie he was in
trouble with the law all the time in
some borough I work alone or something
and he got in a fight in a bar on New
Year's I think or something and a guy
hit him over the head with the bottle
and broke the bottle on his head and and
they said he would die he went to the
hospital they said they told his parents
he's gonna die and he had this intense
night you know I don't know triggered
something good and it's money lots of
seeds probably over on this side
and he had this intense night in
intensive care and and he walked out
mentally a Buddhist he survived and he
didn't die and he came and he started
meditating and it's amazing it's a
beautiful story and now he's the
director of the translation team and
he's very talented linguist his Spanish
I can tell it's good even like don't
understand it
yeah and anyway and he's Tibetan is
really good so he runs the translation
program so anyway when we were splitting
up texts we decided to do in the
Guardian the text and we chose kind of a
difficult one which is called the 60 vs.
I'll tell you the last verse of the 60
you ready gawad the kill wall that's the
last verse that's where it comes from
it's very beautiful it was written by
the gardener and it's the last verse and
he said these are me Dharma guys and
these logic guys they're ours
criticizing our emptiness ideas and they
say Buddha never taught them and and
they say yeah Buddha taught them during
the second turning of the wheel which is
two famous sutras mainly hard-hard sutra
and the diamond cutter my lama called it
the heart sutra but they they say they
don't agree that the Buddha gave those
teachings they say Buddha never gave
those teachings Buddha taught these
basic sutras about the wheel of life and
about the four truths but he never
taught these these emptiness teachings
were not by the Buddha they are written
by other people okay so you know here's
the guardian of 700 years after 700 dark
years these are the dark ages of
Buddhism and he's like
these are cool these are correct because
he saw emptiness directly so we call him
Daria sometimes he just called the Aria
you know and he saw emptiness directly
and he said this those second turn in
the wheel is the right one
those sutras are awesome you know but
how can I convince these ah be Dharma
guys and any he had this really Aria
idea he said I will use their books only
to prove to them that those books teach
emptiness and I will not refer to the
second turning of the wheel
I will restrict the game the game will
be played in the first turning of the
wheel and I will only use first turning
scriptures and I will use those
scriptures to prove to them what is
emptiness what is nirvana and and that's
the game Nix text is this extraordinary
game where somebody proves the second
theory of the wheels correct without
referring to it and he only uses the the
lower school scriptures and it's it's
really awesome and then jetsam coppice
main disciple guilt of jay he's he's you
know the one girl table means the person
who got the throne from tsongkhapa the
second the second person in our lineage
and by the way we are at some copper
lineage and you know people come to me
house the three jewels in New York are
you happy with the three jewels in New
York I said I don't know but if they're
teaching so copper I'm happy and if
they're not teaching so copper I'm
pissed
what is it mean to teach some copper
just emptiness and karma so I've been
assured that every teacher here is
teaching emptiness and karma you don't
have to call it that you can call it
fish and chips I don't care I don't care
you know how you package it and I agree
that you know apparently it's important
to package things different ways for
different generations as in the three
turnings of the wheel
you know who am I to say Buddha
shouldn't have taught second and third
turning
got to change the language you've got to
keep up with your with your city in New
York moves you know move New York's a
moving target so yeah do whatever you
have to do but keep that message in
there okay or I curse you forever okay
like keep the husband in there that the
husband the yelling husband thing that's
gonna be current forever and just keep
that part I don't care then you can do
you know and no Hiawatha okay
but everything else you can do okay like
teach it on your head or I don't care I
really don't care
and and if a CI proved anything it was
that a different packaging for each
generation is a beautiful thing and and
I'll tell you something that I occurred
to me the other day and I to the street
just uh we are the largest international
buddhist organization in the world okay
by accident you know you teach twenty
thousand people your DC i teach three
thousand people a year there's a couple
other groups going on call it seventy
five eighty thousand people a year by
accident because we're presenting it in
modern way we have more people coming
than any other buddhist organization in
the world including the tibetan whatever
you the monastic system which i'm
graduate of but you teach more people
than any other buddhist organization or
person on the planet
you know and it's and we don't think of
it that way we don't go around bragging
about it but but the DC I did a CI
presentation the three jewels
presentation of Buddhism is Buddhism now
okay and I get calls Bertha Velasquez
she got a call from the dialogs office
in Mexico City
can you come and teach us how to teach
business and Buddhism okay and Anton
who's Moscow he got a call from the
dalams office in India saying can you
come and teach us how to teach business
and Buddhism and and it you are you are
Buddhism okay
you are the living Buddhism and there's
a monastic Buddhism the numbers are
shrinking frankly it will be like the
Catholic Church in America it's hard to
find an American Catholic priest there
importing Filipino priests and stuff
like it's just it's not happening and
and I don't know now you're all scared I
can feel it
you are Buddhism in the world
this is Buddhism there's not some other
Buddhism somewhere that's more authentic
or more old or or more traditional you
are Buddhism this is Buddhism you are
keeping Buddhism alive in the world here
at three jewels and your presentation to
modern people is where it's at right now
okay and and it's kind of cool and it's
also kind of scary okay don't get
nervous all right so anyway next text to
go back to his text is this is difficult
the gardener said his famous thing he
said things don't come from themselves
things don't come from something else
things don't come from both and things
don't come from neither and this is very
Nagarjuna
apparently if you've seen emptiness
directly you have this cool style
teaching and and he's like listen dude
nothing comes from itself nothing comes
from something else nothing comes from
both and nothing comes from without a
cause
okay and that stood up for three four
hundred years you know confused people
for three four hundred years by the way
he marks the end of the dark ages
he is his and that announcement marks
the end of the dark ages in Buddhism and
since then it's been light again the
real understanding empty
has survived come back from the
abhidharma dark ages since that day up
to this moment in this room where the
real teacher emptiness has survived okay
that light is in the world okay but
there was an inane germ moment around
300 years later somebody said I think
the gardener was trying to make meter in
the poetry so he left out some words and
everybody his name is Bubba Rebecca and
they said well what did he leave out he
should have said things don't come from
themselves which is obvious you know
like a car doesn't start itself you know
somebody else starts a car a tree
doesn't it takes a seed to to make a
tree grow okay there has to be something
else than the tree to start this tree
that's okay so obviously things don't
start from themselves the tree cannot
grow without a seat and a tree can't
grow with no cause they don't just pop
up you know and but the big question is
do they or do they not come from
something other than the tree does a
tree or does not a tree come from
something other than the tree you tell
me yeah everything comes from something
else okay coffee comes from coffee bean
okay
coffee bean comes from coffee plant
coffee plant comes from coffee being of
less generate you know it goes on so in
the garden I said something wrong when
he said things don't come from something
else cuz they do so Bubba Baker said you
know what he really meant he meant to
say from their own side
he should have added from their own side
and he started a new Buddhism called
lower-middle way SMUD Tantra which has
the word Tantra and it has nothing to do
with Tantra so don't think that the word
is for tantric oh it sounds like sour
Trent ago which is the second school
don't confuse that it has nothing to do
it just means he said it that statement
cannot stand on its own you gotta say
things don't come from other things from
their own time you know the husband who
yells at you is not a husband from his
own time no no Bubba make us please
please add from its own side otherwise
you sell nuts
of course there's a husband in the
kitchen don't go around saying there's
no husband in the kitchen you got the
gardener you've got to add this words
from his own side don't go around
confusing people saying there's no
husband's because we can see there are
husband's okay so he insisted on that
now one of the most exciting moments I
don't know if word if you remember it
but I remember it so we have a student
working on this we have several students
working on this school one is ood Paulo
then our vote with Paulo and he's doing
a special kind of book called totty
totty meditations on emptiness so we
have added that as a separate subject
you know we've given it the status of
the mind only school of the abhidharma
we've created a separate practice
segment of the translation team and she
just translates menti emptiness
meditations and this is a special genre
of literature called dachi which means
emptiness meditations so here's this
she's swimming in emptiness meditations
all day and she's doing this huge book
on on emptiness meditations and she's
sitting there in her quiet way and she's
like Bob will be fake
she's translating Baba Rebecca section
right now and Nick reached the same
thing in his book which is happening the
books are starting to have incest you
know his words book bumped into her book
recently
the mental functions Buddhist psychology
has already come up in two of them it's
already been translated twice and we
have these cool interactions
internetwork happening so anyway she's
sitting there and she says yes I do I
understand this right and I'm like one
you know I'm like why are you
interrupting me in my mind but I said
what she says so the problem is that
bubbly baby
Vanka wants to fix the gardener the
gardener says things don't come from
others there's no husband in the kitchen
at all and then the the lower-middle way
says no no come on the gardener say it
correctly there's no husband in the
kitchen who's not coming from you
because you yelled at your kids last
week yeah say it correctly you know she
said do I have it right I said it's so
good so far so good
yeah that's correct bubbly maker wants
to add from its own time and there's no
husband in the kitchen who's coming from
his own side the gardener should have
added from his own side and then she
says I think what gal sub J is saying is
that you don't have to add those words
because if you add them the person will
think the words come from their own side
and I'm like I'm like I'm like I've been
debating for 25 years in the month
I like Wow she just cracked them the
middle school you know right here in
this room I don't know if you remember
it like I was stunned at that moment I
was like damn you know she just said
something more clear than then thousands
of pages above of America you know if
you add those words if you have if
you're in the gardener you say look
there's no husband in the kitchen and
either the person gets it or they don't
get it because that person's coming from
you
logic has no logic is empty you see I
mean reasons don't have an existence
from their own side so it's no use to
tell somebody
there's no husband in your kitchen who
didn't come for me cuz they won't get
that if they didn't get the first one
got it cuz they're both coming from you
the person you're arguing with is coming
from you about their husbands and it's
so cool you know and she cracked anyway
I thought it's cool
that's the lower-middle way and that's
the kind of thing happening in the in
the room at that moment okay now she
also gets on to a subject which is
called the borders between things okay
and that's what I was teaching last
night and I only got to the very first
subject and I didn't finish I'll finish
in ten minutes okay it's okay I don't if
you have to pee-pee just get up and go
your I hereby allow okay if someone has
a drank a lot of coffee just before you
got here okay don't be shy just stand up
in front everybody and this is what her
book is where we get into the crack
something weirds going on I have a
problem in my house I invented a
sprinkler system from my backyard
because I wanted to go clover cuz I
wanted to go bees and they like clover
so I have a hat of beehive and I
invented a sprinkler system where I tie
cheap Walmart sprinklers to concrete
blocks and move them around the yard and
I thought man I'm so cool and I stayed
like $10,000 then but it kept hitting
the side of the house because the water
pressure changes in my tongue if there's
any water pressure because it's a small
town and so it was getting on the side
of the house it wouldn't leak through
the door and then the floor went Ben so
I hired a late Eleni had it was
advertising in my town my town I was
like 500 people or something and she's a
veteran and she had a single mom so I
thought
I'll give her a try because it would be
patriotic thank you for your service and
she came and she ripped up my floor and
then she left and then my started to cry
didn't you know and I'm like you know it
smells funny in my bedroom you know not
like I don't know it just felt it starts
to smell funny you know and then the
banana started going bad on the counter
in the kitchen you know like little
holes in them and I'm like that's weird
you know and you know then at night I
start to hear these weird things I got
drunk drunk King and I'm like you know
these are cracks in the airplane okay
and you start to get a suspicion now you
start to get a suspicion like hmm stinky
bananas disappearing chewing noises at
night
no and I sit in the kitchen and this
mouse cause up my leg I said I got mice
that's the direct perception okay but
before that you have this suspicion
gross the gardener wants you to start
having a suspicion about reality you see
he wants you to start having suspicions
about things ain't working the way you
thought and he starts with parts okay a
thing is not its parts a thing it's not
all the parts together a thing is not
something else a thing is not nothing
okay
same pattern very nagarjuna and the same
book same first chapter of wisdom in my
way they give all kinds of names to us
forget it
it's called progeny it's just called
wisdom because that's the way an aria
would name their book something sexy not
foundational verses on the middle way
okay
okay really honor so anyway he says
things he's suspicious let's go through
all the things in the world and that's
where we stopped last night okay you are
not all your parts okay physically you
are not all your parts you can say your
energies or you can say your parts okay
then we got to go on to mental things
and what he's saying is the line between
things is suspicious
the line between things is suspicious
you know like where does your arm start
where it is your body's where does your
arm stop where is your body start he
goes there first okay I'm doing last
night's reading now okay from my head
then he goes on to suspicious lines in
your mind okay as I spoke tonight
hopefully the lack of understanding of
the lack of appreciation of the eight
schools really it's eight schools or
nine if you count Tantra that lack of
understanding is like the dark when the
Sun comes up right start the line what
they call Umbria the line between the
light and the dark should be moving
across your brain I'm hoping you see the
light gets more and then that at dawn
and then the darkness recedes but it's
in your own mind you see parts of your
mind are understanding the the schools
better tonight by the end then when you
started and it didn't happen like God
there was a line of light like the line
of dawn coming across the land of your
mind right and then the Guardians like
where's the line what's the line you
know at what point did you understand
25% of the schools and at what point did
you understand 30% of schools and where
exactly in your brain wasn't and where's
the meeting place between that I don't
quite understand all the schools and now
I understand all the schools and you
can't find it there's something weird
going on
there's crunching noises going on you
see I mean you got to start to get like
wow this is weird
yeah where is the line you see when did
I understand the mine only school at
what point in words eloquent I don't
know what happened at what point in his
eloquent description did you start to
understand the mine only school at what
moment it at what syllable at which
sibling in the syllable or or boo you
know like no this is the gardener it's
suspicious you know he's talking at some
moment you can say I understand the mine
school mine always go better but what
moment wasn't and what syllable was he
on or was he at the beginning on the end
of you see and you cannot find it you
can't find the place you see and the
gardener says it's suspicious something
some stuff is going on here he's like
some stuff is going on here
okay so now we covered in mind and we
covered physical stuff we'll save the
person for later and now with what's the
other demon do - uh-huh yeah you can say
that let's go - yeah well we covered the
three kinds of change of things we
covered physical covered mental we're
gonna do people we did people at the
talk last night six elements in the body
stuff like that okay
we covered people and then wood polish
text okay and I I'm sorry you're tired
and I don't care because I like to talk
about it
her text the author who's Choni lama who
is unbelievable he said let's do let's
go onto the emptiness of all the
unchanging things in the universe let's
let's look at the parts of all the
unchanging stuff in the universe empty
space the end of anger in the human
heart and then let's do emptiness okay
like he's
let's let's talk about those boundaries
and we're all like we're already
confused then we're already like
drowning and he's like let's go deeper
let's look at the lines in all the stuff
in the universe that never changes okay
and then he says let's start with coffee
cups you know empty space okay you ready
for that I'll set you up okay and you
better get it right to discuss empty
space he takes a coffee cup well it
takes a kailasha vase
right what if this what a picture
because there wasn't plumbing in ancient
India and every room had a water picture
and the teachers like trying to point to
something that's in every room so it's
always the water picture nowadays it's a
coffee company and very confusingly to
discuss empty space he takes that the
the cracks in empty space he takes a
coffee cup why confusing word for $100
or did I just save $100 Tim got it 5050
Hannibal and Hannibal come on give it to
me yeah good but Tim give me the other
half good say it more clearly good
empty space is not the distance from one
side to the other
forget done that's not space that's not
space in Buddhism okay but Tony Lama
took confused everyone takes a coffee
cup you see and because he's gonna talk
about the emptiness of empty space okay
and he's like let's take coffee cups and
then half the people in the room already
misunderstood him because they're
thinking the space between the the two
walls of the coffee cup that's not the
emptiness of that's not the empty
face its the space that coffee cup is
taking whether it's full or not whether
that there's any edge doesn't matter so
fifty-fifty okay actually Tim did 75 and
how about this right Bob he's new so
I'll give you 50 okay got it
and then he says something cool so
here's the here's the saucer okay and
here's the coffee cup okay
do they both have empty space yes or no
I mean I heard two couple mutterings
come on take a chance have empty space
they both occupy empty space okay got it
now does the empty space occupied but
occupied by the coffee cup touch the
empty space occupied by the saucer and
where's the line between them you see
who wears the line between the copper
atoms where's the line between the
understanding of words texts and the
mist and didn't talk about it yet
where's the line between the emptiness
of the saucer and the emptiness of the
coffee cup you cannot find it and that's
a crack in the wing something weirds
going on I can smell something fishy I'm
hearing Roger yeah I mean it's very cool
okay and who's gonna go there to the
emptiness empty space and he says I'm
not done with you guys yet he says I'm
not done with you guys yet let's talk
about the anger you're never gonna have
after you understand what your husband's
come from let's say it again okay I'm
not talking about the anger I'm talking
about the anger you're never gonna have
again once you understand the husband
thing once you understand the emptiness
of your partner you cannot ever get
angry again in theory okay once you
understand that any irritating thing
your partner says is coming from you
how can you be irritated at them
okay got it can we say there's such a
thing as irritation
your partner occasionally yeah okay can
we say that the partner that you
irritated at is coming from their son no
you cannot say that but that's human
nature that's why we're still in the
design room okay that's why we're still
so sorry can we say that there's
actually no partner that you're
irritated at that's coming from their
side got it okay can we say that then an
irritating bar a sign I'll take it back
yeah can we say that an irritating boss
that you meet when you go to open the
coffee shop in the morning once in a
while it's coming from you or coming
from them can we say this one that's not
coming from them can we say yeah
every irritating boss is not coming from
Denham okay now what's the line between
the absence of irritating boss that's
coming from their own side and the
absence of irritating partner who's not
coming from the outside where's the line
between those two emptinesses and
where's the line between the lack of
anger that you feel towards the two
because you can't be angry at something
you created yourself got it okay that's
where he goes he goes - what's the line
between the two emptinesses okay then he
goes deeper he says and what's the line
between the two things that aren't there
and then he goes deeper and he says
where's the line between the anger that
will never happen towards the boss and
the anger that will never happen towards
the husband where's the line between
them it goes deeper where's the line
between the anger that you'll never have
at the bus because you understand the
boss is like the pen and the anger you
will never have towards the husband
because you know that the husband's like
the pen as perceived directly in the
state of seeing emptiness directly
where's the line between those two empty
two empty people relative to the direct
presumption emptiness and where's the
line between the anger you will never
have because you saw the emptiness of
one directly and you saw the other
indirectly okay where's the line between
the two angers that you will never have
again which is called Nirvana okay
where's the line and you can't find it
so he says you ready here's here's the
ultimate this is where we're at in
expect if you recall somebody says to
the gardener what's the definition of
Nirvana and he says that direct
understanding of samsara and he says you
figure it out he's like you know and it
blows up the lower school they go crazy
they got like what you know the violence
when you disappear you know no more pain
everything's gone it's uh uh the fun is
when you understand some song the
emptiness is sons are okay and that
blows up this tech we're at the point in
his next text where the whole thing
blows up because the gardener was to
define Nirvana as understanding the
emptiness of samsara okay got it and
it's very uncomfortable for the
lowest-cost
okay I'm not done yet we got two more
okay just two more then we'll take a
break and then I'll upp and after that
I'll give you an inspiring talk about
how to keep this going how to have 1,000
three trolls around the world 3000
jewels
okay uh this is kind of cool okay beg
Kramer he's our resident nudnik guy and
he won't let anything go he's like
unbelievable
you can't I can't get anything past him
he'll say geshe-la that's not really
correct you know it doesn't make sense
you know and I'm like I know but I was
just you know trying to finish the class
no no so he's doing a text called
Siddhanta say Siddhanta it comes from
Siddha and anta and it means the study
of all the schools of thought Buddhist
or non-buddhist the study of all
religions and so it's a traditional
subject in the Buddhist literature
called the study of all religions in the
world and modern Siddhartha's include
Christianity for example okay like the
ones written since 1750 or something
1800 you can find them in the TBR sieve
database these modern Siddhanta street
science in you know Christianity and
once you get past 1750 or 1700 they they
they just treat Indian schools of
thought and they compare the beliefs of
all the schools on this paper and
20-something Hindu schools like
different kinds of Sanka
okay and different kinds of Jane's
different kinds of vaishnavites
different kinds of Shai bites and every
possible idea about emptiness so cool
cool literature you know what did they
think is emptiness not just Buddhist but
what is the soul mean to and the lack of
a soul mean to non-buddhist in India and
it's very very beautiful and and it's
tempting as you go through his book to
try to categorize our beliefs you know I
grew up Christian I still go to church
and and I grew up believing in science I
was taught and and huh at school I was
taught science in the church I was
taught Christianity and and where did
those beliefs fit in these thirty belief
systems they're at their blow the first
one science is below the first one
science is more primitive than the
lowest school treated in Siddhanta okay
and it's kind of shocking when you're
like oh my gosh I grew up in a like in
Buddhism they call okay $20 because I'm
afraid you might know it Lalo let's lay
low $20 give give her back a $20 yeah
I'm uh my beliefs that I grew up with
what I was taught in my school is it's
called in Buddhism barbarian which comes
from bud butter which is an old witch
caught insult to people who can't speak
your language
in Berbers Berbers in morocco became
called butBut and in the next a long
story ask mr. nami which is his real
name
gommi anyway so we're down below the
lowest school of ancient times you know
and part of that classification is
because we are not taught to think
clearly okay
part of that classification as you
studied that book is that we lack the
basic tools of logic we are not trained
in what makes sense
formally we're not trained in how to
make a statement how to make a reason
ACI 13 the one you hate okay but that's
the one that's gonna graduate you to sit
down
you know then at least you'll be in the
ballpark okay if you can think clearly
okay anyway his book has a big emphasis
on
Chucky Chucky Chucky Chuck chatter mudra
yeah the four seals and its seals of
approval
you know mudra has many meanings this is
mother are dumb budding boo-boo big in
the new depth these are all called mudra
in Tantra mudra is your partner your
tantric partner it's called mudra but it
also it means feel but in in Siddhanta
it means Seal of Approval
if a book has four qualities you should
read it and if they don't have phone
call this you should ignore it okay if a
movie has for these poor you should
watch it if it doesn't have these four
you should only watch it if you're
really tired what are the four and I
listed them here okay number one if if a
teaching doesn't point out to you that
you are dying at this moment that you
are two hours closer to your death after
this talk then don't go to the tongue
okay if it's not directly stated or
implied that you are dying as we speak
don't go it's not relevant to your life
okay got it
that's the first one second one
everything is pain okay pain is pain we
did with Coco that's a great yoga class
you're a great yo I enjoyed your class
we had it here it was so pleasant
it's like anyway at the end of class we
said shanti shanti shanti this is from
the open oopah nish odd which means sit
down at the feet of your teacher
oopah near knee down son sit your butt
subbu pani shut and it comes in the
upanishads in it shanti shanti shanti
which we say at the end of yoga it means
look
three kinds of trouble going on number
one obvious trouble back aches headaches
irritating friends second pleasant
things okay we're gonna you know if you
had a nice dinner and in Buddhism
encounter suffering because you will get
hungry the next night it can't stay
suffering or change third one yeah
everything suffering you know we we are
dying as we sit here you know we're
dying we're all dying as we sit here New
York is dying as we sit here you know so
these are if a teaching doesn't inform
you that you are in trouble don't go
don't listen to it okay it's something
if someone doesn't try to tell you
you're in trouble you got to do
something now while you're in this piece
of meat do something with it cuz you
ain't gonna be here very long okay and
those of us like John and me who have
air conditioning we can tell you I mean
we were just here yesterday the three
jewels was opening Annie Palmer who now
has cancer and is having brain
treatments as we speak it goes things go
okay if the if the teaching doesn't talk
about that it's not the three jewels
okay second thing third each other seals
of the Buddha let's do well selfless
means it ain't coming from its own side
it ain't coming from its own cuts I got
it
the situation is not coming your body's
not coming from its own size okay who
made it
mortal you did okay you weren't kind
enough to other people for every meal
you eat you must be giving to or you
will die for every meal you eat you must
be giving to to poor people or you will
die
it's that's the arithmetic okay and if
and if you go to a center and they're
not teaching that it's not the three
jewels and it's not a CRE
okay it doesn't have the seal of
approval
last one by the way you don't have to
keep repeating this every single class
I'm just saying that institution that
white room should be teaching this for
and if you are I love you and if you're
not huh okay last one
peace peace means if you figure it out
that the pen is coming from you
eventually you'll become a Buddha who
can serve countless beings at the same
time in the same hour you can serve
billions of people you open up three
billion joules at the same time you know
and if and if an institution if a space
it's not talking about these deeper
things it's not a Buddhist space and and
I want a Buddhist space that's all
that's all I really want you know how
you do it you know call it bowling and
emptiness I'm good with that I actually
tried it in New York I told Hector we
tried to do bowling and emptiness it
didn't work out but you got to try
everything okay last one I love this one
then we'll stop and we'll take a pee-pee
break okay say J who is amazing guy
that's his photo his ancestors are
Japanese and he was born in Guadalajara
and they moved
I think after World War one they moved
to Guadalajara and so he looks Japanese
but he's a nice he was brought up in
Mexico but he was trained in Sweden I
think No Sweden Australia he has a
degree in economics from Austria he's
amazing and he's helping to run BCI and
to run the college for DCI teacher
training and he's just a brilliant guy
and one day he said in addition to my
other duties can I become a translator
I'm like yeah I'll take you and we were
digging around for books for him and we
were in Austria in Germany there's very
smart people there
right we're gonna be there we have three
of them here three and four then five
thank you for coming by the way Baron
Pyotr and beget any Yuta who are you
anyway thank you for coming anyway we're
gonna be there next week in Vienna and
so anyway I had a very crucial moment we
had already decided the eight
translators we had already divided up
the eight schools and then they came to
me two Austrians Norbert and Renata and
they said we need a book on karmic
correlations you know I love your all
your books very nice very cool but we
need to know what to do you know can you
just translate a book that says do this
get this do this get this do this get
this you know is there any book like
that
it's called karmic correlations right
and there's two famous books one is
called Karma be Bunga it was spoken by
Lord Buddha and it's very cut and dry he
says what do you want and somebody says
financial independence he says okay
karma is this okay what's your next one
and somebody says I want to be beautiful
and he said oh do this then somebody
says I have a back problem oh do this
you know and it's all he asks a question
then he answers himself and it's like
the hundred most common questions that
he got and it was collected into a Sutra
and and so we're translating that and
then there's another book by Dharma
Rokita who is the teacher of at Isha and
we're not tisha I left for Tibet you
know
his teacher gave him a poem and it's
called Sandra Carlo
yeah the crown of knives its
mistranslated as well and it refers to a
story in the first Center where a young
man is disrespectful to his mother and
it gets worse and worse and eventually
he accidentally kicked her in the head
and then it's like a science fiction
story but in the end he's in a dark
castle at night and a wheel of knives is
descending on his head like a helicopter
blade and in the moment before it
descends he says may I take on the pain
of all beings I'm okay with it I kicked
my mother in the head it was back then
but I'm okay cut my head but I take on
the pain of all beings and then the
wheel stops okay anyway so auntie shouts
teacher called his book the wheel of
knife and it refers to this story from
the first karmic correlation book by
Buddha and it's a holistic army
correlations they were plagiarized by
for no dollars Geshe Michael in a book
called the diamond 46 correlations or
something I just took him one by one out
of out of our teachers teachers book
okay they're all ripped off and so
anyway that's a nice text and then I
finished okay the thing that we just
reached which was so sweet was I don't
know if you remember but it was then by
the way this is how you tell the guy had
a llama this is how you can tell the
author had a llama he says what's the
Karma when you work your ass off for
your llama and you do everything
possible to make them happy and they
still are pissed off at you you know
they still never satisfied you know they
keep complaining criticizing you you
know you try to make Hector happy you do
everything he gave you
you know you make the space of everybody
you work your ass off you lose your job
everything you're living on nothing and
people are complaining about the water
cooler you know and and then they said
what's a comma for that you know what is
the Karma for that you're trying to
please the public and you just get more
criticism or you know you're trying to
please specifically your teacher and
they keep saying it's not good enough
and I had this for 30 years okay so I
understand and it seems to be a common
Karma okay like you tried so hard to
please the public to please the students
to please the people you dedicate your
life to it and all you get is criticism
you know and then he he says of course
it's your fault well okay just tell me
what I did so I don't have it in my next
life you know and he says you disturbed
other people's holy work you disturbed
other people's meditation you you
disturb their study you criticize their
teachers is a list of things that you
did you know and and it's mainly
disturbing your fellow students peace of
mind or you know they're trying to
meditate you're making noise outside or
you know they're trying to study and you
say let's go to a movie instead
you know you disturb other people's
stuff and you disturb your teachers you
disturb the attempts of the three jewels
to serve New York and that's a specific
Karma law that no matter what you're
trying to make do to try to make other
people happy they criticize you okay and
what I enjoyed from that presentation I
don't know if it hit you the same way it
hit me but he said and never criticize
never blame it on the person who's
hassling you never ever my mom used to
say never ever blame it on the people
writing things about you on the
you know no responses no eloquent
defenses you know it's not them okay the
criticisms coming because you disturbed
your fellow students in their meditation
or you you upset other people at the
center and don't bother defending
yourself okay you created it and don't
make extra trouble for yourself by
criticizing that people are criticizing
you see what I mean it's very it was
very moving to me that he said and don't
and don't ever get the least pissed off
at your lover who's criticizing you all
day cuz it's not them and then you're
just gonna son summarize it it's just
gonna continue you see so I I just
struck me very powerfully a
understanding it's coming from you be
never ever blame someone else even the
person who's criticizing you like chill
chill out because that's a it's not
where it's coming from and be if you
even blame them mentally you're creating
more
okay got it take a break take it there
you just covered all the bit of school
[Applause]
I propose 15 minutes of questions and
answer if you're in the mood and then
then I'll wrap up and you know try to
get you excited about tomorrow typically
that means it was a good teacher anybody
else any question any subject I don't
care
silly or serious that's okay
but loud yeah he did say that and that
takes us to a higher school you ready
okay so there's two kinds of navona word
for zero dollars that seems to be
working tonight better know
will remain in there no but you're right
that's also it's also done so there's
two kinds of Nirvana one is classically
called
chain yong-dae which means with
with something left over afterwards and
then luck mayne Youngjae means nothing
left over afterwards and in the lower
schools in all schools of Buddhism you
reach nirvana it's not enlightenment you
reach nirvana when you cannot have a
negative emotion so anger is stopped
forever you get there by understanding
that the people who piss you off are
coming from you okay which is which is
how emptiness cures your negative
emotions okay
that's all so once you understand that
the partner who irritates you once in a
while is coming from you then slowly
your anger the first time you hear it in
a class the anger is is cracked and it
can't be as healthy as it was before you
see that's the great thing of the three
jewels even if people go home after one
night hit him with that do the husband
in the kitchen if you need I'll leave
Peter here and were you the husband or
the wife okay I thought so I heard he
had a wig on but I I'm not going there
anyway the minute someone hears that the
people who irritate them are coming from
them whether they believe it or not
where they understand it or not it
cracks the ability to have full-scale
anger you can you are cursed from the
moment you hear emptiness once you
cannot be fully angry ever again if
someone suggests that the pen is coming
from you then any fool will apply it to
their personal relationships you see and
then after that you can't be as angry as
you used to get you'll still get angry
but not not as good as you used to do
okay
and if you keep working along those
lines you keep coming to three jewels
you keep meditating you hear the pan
over and over and over again you see
that two husbands get over and over
again at some point it's so internalized
you cannot get angry it's not possible
to get angry okay and that's called
Nirvana in the lower schools that's
called Nirvana with remainder because
you still have your body which was
created by negativity you still have a
mortal body and it will still cause you
suffering so it's not the end of pain in
the sense of the end of pain of the body
you still have pain but you are not
creating new pain you see I mean so
there's a the first argument in the
first time Lamas I'll be damned in Texas
is it true that in our heart was killed
in a bordello for Dale whorehouse you
know you know and a bars or something
and they say yeah it's true
he was it our hearts still have
remainder they still live in the body
okay then they walk around for ten years
twenty years and then that body dies and
then they're free that's all be Dharma
okay that's nirvana so first you achieve
Nirvana
with with with something left over still
some suffering there but you're not
creating new one and then you achieve
Nirvana without we made there now
highest school
it's qward you want to go there are you
ready
you got to do it right I trust you not
from me he took three thousand dollars
of my money in one day
[Applause]
nice
what's the remainder that you don't have
at that moment it comes back of course
yeah that's that yeah that's cool
but but if you push the highest score
person they would still say that guy's
not in our heart it's not real their
mother yes I mean because that comes
long after you see emptiness directly
and seeing emptiness directly speeds up
the process of not getting angry at your
husband asked him hot question hot
question that is hot
eight level bodies top level out of ten
levels is nirvana on the body surface
right very nice
with or without remainder well by that
time I think you can see emptiness that
will so you could take both I guess
you know no actually it would be without
because at the eighth level things no
longer can appear that's coming from
their own side okay and then eight nine
and ten are called doxa Dartmouth uh
yeah in his text okay for fifty dollars
what's the special mind only word for
those buddy suffer damn what's it mean
4030 yeah okay okay pretty good they
have a special name this especially the
infinite power achievers okay another
question you already have never never
start a question that way just just
adding I'll see I missed New York I
really do miss me I miss the coffee
shops mostly now that you have one I'll
try okay but I do miss New York and it's
kind of weird to come once a year yeah
that's that really sorry yeah
I'll try but my time is you know my time
is really really crazy like every five
minutes every 10 minutes is really it's
very weird my life is very weird
fight I don't have five minutes
is opinion about the emptiness a young
like of emptiness is self-existent in a
sense yes yeah okay I got a I got do you
want to do you want to try to do the
magician thing are you sure
okay you start now you can understand
the lower-middle way from the example of
a magic show and you probably heard it
somewhere in some of my classes but you
go ahead so one such crowd which is the
original meaning of the word mantra
magic words by a magician abracadabra in
Syria Arabic Persian and through the
powder
appears to be a cow or a horse or I'll
up in whatever it's a elephant that's
more grandiose right so everyone's like
right all of a sudden there's an
elephant there right and so while he's
performing the trick someone's walking
by and so first school middle-way
says this explains three things three
levels
Arya's nice but which is which
I always have trouble with this so you
explain now we're getting there done the
husband appears to come from his own
side and they believe it yeah it's like
the Aria in the dirt
because they it's not appearing any
other way okay so but the difference
above Aviv eka is the stick is the raw
data there is a stick there that's
that's the big difference he would say
he's you could call it the fifty-fifty
school the data is coming this way you
you created an elephant but there's
gotta be a stick and his whole thing is
to stick so this metaphor is the
lower-middle way metaphor they use it
they're the guys who use it because
because they need the stick that's all
they don't care about the rest they need
to say the color and shape of the
husband is coming from the husband and
then your mind is interpreting your mind
is seeing yelling but the sounds are
coming from here and your mind
organizes them into criticism of you but
there are sounds coming from the husband
that are not coming from you and that's
lower-middle way whoa whoa what well
they would they would what they would
say is in the kitchen when the husband
yells at you that sounds the sibilance
the vowels to consonants those are not
coming from you that's raw data coming
from the husband then your karma is
organizing those into criticism and if a
person walked in who didn't have that
Karma they would say your husband is
correctly chastising you you thin I mean
that's all you can call them the 50/50
well now nouns are typically more on
Cuba what's that for $50 damn yeah there
are they overlap there are guys who
they're called the mind only ish lower
middle range okay cool yeah go ahead
bunny we miss you how he did where's
your man telling me to loser for not
being a
but maybe he has some lesson - I don't
know it's a good question and it came up
in Nick's text to 60 verses and I did
this brilliant thing where I counted
them and there's 61 you know and I was
like Geshe Michaels gonna fix me a guide
you know you know it's not 60 versus 61
because I was trying to figure out the
last verse in I counted and I kept
counting and it's 61
and it turns out the first verse doesn't
count which is the praise of the Buddha
at the beginning of the text and it says
I praise the Buddha who taught emptiness
in light of cause and effect you see
with an end to copper who wrote the
praise of the Buddha for teaching
dependence right he says the same thing
so you can't really praise the Buddha
for teaching emptiness if you don't
place the Buddha at the same time for
teaching where your husband comes from
you see you got to teach both and and
those the fact that in the gardener in
that famous you know book the first
thing he does is praise the Buddha for
teaching where the husband comes from a
and then what the husband is not and you
have to teach him together
so that's the answer you get more points
for teaching it that way you get more
points for teaching emptiness in light
of karmic seeds which is why three
jewels teaches the marriage of emptiness
and karma so is that question you just
kind of
okay did Tim help you with your hair
just kidding I'm just I'm just jelly
okay okay
no problem me and John are just jealous
[Laughter]
yeah it's cool cuz you know I was
telling Hector my teaching has improved
on tour which I start tomorrow morning
at 6:30 or some because I'm struggling
with translations on there you know all
day so there's some beautiful discussion
of that and it's called Nina 4:20 it's
only worth 20 yeah the discrepancy
capital D 20 bucks more
it's called the discrepancies so what
people translate as dualism is a kind of
a mistranslation of a word mean none
which means double appearance it really
means discrepancy between what you see
and what's really there okay so when we
say dualism it does not it does not and
it does not refer to the dualism between
the observer and the object that's not
what dualism means in Buddhism dualism
means the object the husband appears to
be angry he did he decided to criticize
me
that's the appearance and the reality is
my mind is creating a husband who's
criticizing me so there's what appears
and what's real are not the same there's
a discrepancy it looks like your husband
decided to criticize you but what really
happened was you yelled at your kids
last week you think I mean so there's a
disconnect and that's the meaning of
dualism and Buddhism now in the direct
perception emptiness Vipassana and by
the way the partner is a corruption of
the word Vipassana in pali and and I
studied it I studied it from Co Inca who
invented it in 1973 okay and before you
were born and it doesn't mean watching
the breath okay it means the direct
presumption emptiness with schemata with
the deep meditation now when you're
seeing emptiness directly you can only
perceive that you cannot perceive an a
changing thing you can you are you are
having communion with an unchanging
thing so during those 20 minutes it's
impossible to perceive a changing
thing there for a person who's seeing
emptiness directly cannot be aware of
themselves because Michael is a changing
thing you see the mean and when they say
that the subject disappears it's not
literal it's just that you can't be
aware that you're there because if you
were it would kick you out of emptiness
if you have the thought Michael or if
you the most dangerous thought is I did
it you get literally kicked out of the
experience so you're actually in a way
you're trying to sustain the non
perception of me by staying in emptiness
you see what I mean
so that's all you're not aware of your
mind but the mind is there but you can't
be aware of it you see I mean that's all
that's all that's the subject/object
thing okay there is a subject there is
an object the word for subject is object
holder session and deja some people who
say that the sub there's a subject no
I'm no subject it's foolish because the
to say that in Sanskrit is impossible
okay it's not possible the word for
subject this object holder okay anyway I
want to wrap up and so tomorrow there'll
be a big conference which I I praised
him and Herto for deciding to do it I'll
tell you just a little bit about the
history of ACR so and the three jewels
is really a CI in New York so I I don't
know I I taught the eighteen courses
foundational courses non Tantra courses
up to 290 99 or something and then I
made an announcement it was a famous
night I remember it's kind of shocking
for anybody and we went past the Quaker
Church I said which is where we did it I
think we had 85 people and we had work
so
hard to get up to 85 people and they
went to the we did the 18 courses and
then I I know I made this big
announcement I'm going on through your
retreat and the whole place kind of blew
up and you know it was hard for all of
us and so me and John still well we had
a meeting I think I was telling these
guys down in Wall Street my last day in
New York before going on to your retreat
and I had a meeting with him and I he
said I have two questions guest number
one okay I said what he says we got to
put this online but I don't know anybody
who who can do it because it was you
know when the wheel was still and not
invented yet and I said don't worry I
have a woman she does IT for a large
company her name is Joanna you're gonna
like her and so anyway I put them
together they got married later they had
kids I take credit in fact we just had
some time together and then the second
thing I said I said so you promise once
a week at the three jewels you'll
collect all the students together and
play my recordings of the 18 courses and
he said no and I'm like I'm leaving you
got to do what I asked
he says we're gonna teach it ourselves
and I'm like oh you know and they did
and they thought they started teaching
the 18 courses John started teaching the
18 courses or three jewels but he said
to me and you should know the history he
said guys like we will have a CI we and
at that time the policy was anyone who
takes a course can teach it once you
finish a CI one you're allowed to teach
it after that and he said that policy
has to go you know and and there will be
no ACI home office and I said what
he says I don't want the liability if a
student harasses a woman in the class or
someone steals money or someone doesn't
pay their taxes I don't want to have the
legal liability that people are gonna
come to me and sue me
you know I have a family I have he had a
small street job shishi job and told my
own anyway he said I don't want the I
don't want the responsibility
there will be no ACI home office if
you're ok with that
I'll do it and I said you know you're
the only guy God so I guess it's ok and
and that's what happened and so ever
since then if you took an ACI course you
could teach it and we and I encouraged
people to teach it now no it has
happened in days gone by that teachers
abuse students either emotionally
sexually or financially and I think we
all have felt that it's come time that
we have to have a home office we have to
regulate who teaches we have to make
sure they are following we call it the
four legs of the table if I don't forget
first when you got to know your stuff
nobody knows their stuff like ACI nobody
in the world I'm that's ok that's we
don't have to talk about that secondly
you have to learn how to present you
know you have to learn how to speak in
front of the public we have to give you
some training of you know how not to
stutter how not to say oh all the time
how not to say bad words in the class
and stuff like that ok presenting
thirdly we have to teach you management
skills because running a three jewels is
much different from teaching a
co-teaching a CI is easy running three
jewels is impossible you know finding
the money renting signing the contracts
you know getting people here you know
not going bankrupt it takes management
skills advertising marketing
relationships all kinds of business
stuff that a modern yoga teacher or a
modern Dharma teacher should know or you
will not be successful you can be a nice
teacher you can know your stuff but if
you cannot organize a three jewels you
you will fail you'll never teach a lot
of people you see so you kind of have to
be a business person you have to be a
good speaker and if you're not naturally
those two we our goal is to make you you
see
that's different from the three jewels
it's it's a HCI teacher training so a
you have to know your stuff every a shy
student knows their stuff they pass
their homeworks they did their quizzes I
had one guy he did all the courses in
one weekend and he wrote out every
single answer off the internet by hand
it was extraordinary
and we still failed him but you know who
was so anyway first you gotta know your
stuff there's not a question here you
all know your stuff we're talking about
stuff they don't debate in the monastery
tonight you know you are already going
deeper than then the way I guess you
carrying it goes already tonight we went
there okay so that's okay we got that
but secondly you know you're either a
born teacher or you're not a born
teacher if you're not a born teacher
does that mean you can never teach no we
should have a good training where people
who are feel nervous or people not
comfortable with presenting but who are
very fine people we just teach them how
to teach you know so that's gotta have
that second thing right then third thing
is management skills you know advertise
your class there are many many
extraordinary teachers yoga teachers -
nobody comes to their classes because
they don't know how to get the word out
they don't know how to attract people I
heard about a cool model today
what's it called yoga for the people you
gotta have these kind of ideas about how
to manage your your business you know
and your business is to help people and
lose money trust me okay now I mean your
business is we are not in business to
take people's money we are in business
to save people from death you know and
if that means you have to spend your own
money for the rest of your life I don't
have a problem we're done but if if you
learn the third thing well the place
should run itself
financially it can sustain itself okay
you're not begging rich people for a few
dollars like I did this morning and
you're not you know the place is is is
sustaining itself we need to train
people to do that a yoga teacher
training that doesn't have these two
it's not going to be successful
I heard 80% of people who take yoga
teacher trainings never teach okay only
20% become successful teachers so I
don't want that here you see we want to
teach people the content teach them how
to teach and it doesn't mean you don't
have your own style you know I'm not
gonna do the wig that Peter did I don't
have the courage you know I'm just
saying we all have our own style
whatever system we have for teacher
training should not crush people's
individual style you Hector has a
certain Flair I don't have that Flair
I have a different thing and you should
teach within your own style we shouldn't
be like like this you know so it's a
balance we want to teach people to teach
within their own style in a cool way
okay or in a boring way if that's their
style and then okay not really
some people are really drying they're
very popular okay so third one is that
you know how to get the word out and
there's many many yoga teachers who are
very
very good teachers and know what no one
knows about them I
one of the most irritating moments in my
life was in Phoenix not long back and I
gave I gave a three four days ago I gave
a week of classes at the Jewish
Community Center one room and then I
went to a yoga class and this guy goes I
guess Ibaka you're here you're in
Phoenix I said yeah and he said are you
gonna teach in Phoenix
I just finished 10 days this is the day
after and I'm like I just taught for 10
days he said I didn't hear about it and
my own teacher he was very dear he never
took money from a student in his life
when I offered him my bank account book
the first day I met him he threw it at
me he hit me on the head with it he
threw it back at me and he said I want
your money you know and he refused to
take money for 30 years
he taught every day four or five hours
refused to take money she knows so
anyway there's there's people who can't
manage okay you got a you got a
management class you gotta have this
okay
these are the three things you gotta
know your stuff be able to teach and be
able to manage it a three jewels okay
and if you don't have those three you're
gonna get in trouble okay his policy was
I don't want to be famous but I don't
want a single person in the region who
wants to come to not hear about it you
see I don't want you pushing me on
people I don't want to be in the
magazines I don't want to he refused to
travel for example he said let that
didn't come to me but he said if it
happens that a student in New York City
who wanted to meditate didn't hear about
this Regis you failed you know we were
like oh god you know so that was his
policy and and he kept heard his whole
life okay anyone who might want to come
should hear that's all
but we're not selling it you know we're
not trying to push people that was the
third thing now the last one is we call
professional behavior and it boils down
to sex and money
okay as so much of life don't abuse the
students don't take advantage of
students sexually you know respect
people this way how you touch them how
you teach them Yoga is especially
delicate you know respect people that
way and pay your taxes keep good
accounts be accountable to your sponsors
when they say how did my money gets
spent you go within an hour you can say
here's here's where your money went you
know if it were me I would have your
books online life if it were me I would
have your books online life and let
people criticize you you know Hector
bought a coffee yeah I bought a coffee
okay but at least everyone knows I
bought a coffee you know I mean if it
were me if I had the choice your books
would be live online and open to the
world
anyone can see how are you spend every
dollar here and I think that would be
the coolest thing and I keep trying to
find someone to program it anything
I don't probably we could do it okay so
those professional behavior okay
financial responsibility accountability
personal accountability okay and we have
to train people to do them okay so for
me ACI teacher training which we will
embark on tomorrow post John still I
don't want the legal liability okay I
mean what we're trying to do tomorrow
for the first time really is to say we
do have ACI we are responsible for our
teachers and and we trained them well
and then we don't release them on the
world now I I think there should be a
grandfathering process John Brady
shouldn't have to come back and do the
18 courses again okay there should be a
process by which you select
senior teachers because you got to have
somebody to start with Hector is
probably okay and you got to have you
got to have a base but then other people
should go through training I and and
these are the elements you're going to
decide on tomorrow and I think it's
exciting that I won't be here and I I
just want you to think about this for
items okay and how did I believe there
should be some kind of my partner
Veronica is a massage therapist she has
to do I think it's 30 hours a year of
continuing education units CEUs and I
think we should have something similar
because I think there should be some way
that senior teachers check back in with
the home office from time to time they
get updates I've had people who studied
with me who have not come to a class in
ten years and and they're hopelessly are
out of date too because this is a moving
target this stuff changes every
afternoon and I think there should be in
the system there should be some way that
and there should be some kind of
evaluation without being to Catholic
Church II what do you call imprimatur
there shouldn't be someone leaning over
your shoulder making sure you say the
right words you know you gotta be ory
and you got to use your own language if
you still want to say coffee you should
say coffee you know that should it's a
delicate balance between fostering
creativity and preventing abuse you know
some good luck yeah question because
it's the first time the international
community for AC is coming in together
we don't just produce teachers and teach
ACI content ACI is also responsible for
the content
which all these things are held online
way that is presented in a way that is
marketed some nonprofit work like the
donate yeah or the retreats so I see I
as an identity is more than the courses
and the teachers more and more focus on
that courses on the engine they should
also use the opportunity since we're all
together to identify what we're all the
facets of a current ACI yeah and we
should we go forward can you share what
what you would see because we need
financial sustainability yeah we need a
good PR good presenting but can you
share with us what you would like us to
become my habit is to try to do too much
as you may have noticed so I would say
tomorrow limit yourselves to what you
can do successfully in one day if you
get too spread out nothing will happen
so do some core thing have some core
goal whatever your core goal is I think
it's teacher training you know focus on
that nail it down first and then go to
other things like what is our charitable
work or things like that but I think I
might tendency at these kind of
conferences is to throw a hundred things
out and then what happens is nothing
happens so I would say try by the end of
the day to come to a consensus on what
you would like teacher training to be
and then at the teacher trainings we can
go we can go deeper I think we don't
exist in a vacuum
you know 108 lives project or things
like that Dhaka
these are ACIP these are a big part of
of what we should be but I'd kind of
like to hear what you want and what you
think because you actually have more
contact with the American public than I
do and I think I'd like to see what you
guys come up with but what I'd like to
do is get a teacher training going this
year I don't want more disk
Russians in 2019 I want something
happened in 2019 where we begin to
certify teachers and take responsibility
for the teachers and the teachers know
what they're supposed to do you know so
I think that that's my that's my feeling
and then I hope it continues I hope that
I hope this stuff continues I want more
thing I mean it's a big issue in DCI
right now is we took a CI to foreign
countries where people are not Buddhist
and they don't want Buddhism and some of
the best is DCI teachers I can think of
the Bulgarians gilligan even yogi cadre
of anyone in here they don't want to be
Buddhists and there are two of the best
DCI teachers in the world and they they
told me we don't want to be Buddhists
we're happy
Pinoy Greek Orthodox whatever but we
love DCI we love the ideas we want to
teach DCI
so I there's a there's a challenge at
the CI right now is we have to be
strictly secular we cannot mention
Buddhism we cannot confuse the audience
and we are attracting the President of
Argentina Macri Mauricio Macri we had a
program for him and when he was mayor of
Buenos Aires and he would not come if he
thought we were Buddhist DCI so I
there's a there's another issue for me
which is how to keep this naci separate
but still keep a CI available to these
young people because if a CI leaks into
DCI people like that will not come and
we would never have a chance to teach
the current President of Argentina it
would never happen if it was Buddhists
do you see so I need to and it's a very
very difficult job
to be Buddhist but not mention Buddhism
you know and and we teach in many Muslim
countries we teach about five thousand
Muslims every year I just wrote a major
book with a Muslim author and it's in
Russian right you translated it and we
taught in Dubai if we had mentioned
Buddhism we would have been thrown out
and there's other countries that are
even more straight so you know just keep
in mind and Tim knows the issues just
respect try to figure out how we keep
keep that you know that we're not rating
DC ice people and kind of ruining that
gig which is a business case but at the
same time the funnel allows for there's
DCI people who want to become nuns for
example and they did write cinema so you
know it happens and but it's a delicate
it's an issue that you have to and it's
gonna be difficult but you have to try
to respect that our mission is bigger
than Buddhism and and and the ACI they
kind of have to be kept this thing from
each other and it's gonna be a challenge
it's a major challenge so that that's
one of your impossible that's the second
thing I'd say you know I don't think a
CI should be limited or three jewels
should be limited to the a CI courses
they are very looking back at them now
they look almost I don't want to say
prehistoric but I just taught level what
was it seven for the first time in 23
years and yeah I haven't looked at it
for 23 years and and I'm thinking this
needs some kind of modernizing or
something you know so the basic courses
are
beautiful the information is beautiful
but I think you've gotta get more
creativity going you know and and then
when you go to do a business program
you've got to change your suit you gotta
change your clothes and and as a teacher
you gotta be good at that
okay it's as if you could teach eight
different schools at the same time you
get the point
yeah so be brave be adaptable don't go
to a corporate gig and start talking
about Buddhism okay all right and don't
do it a steai program and and teach
something from DCI that I'm gonna teach
four years from now in that city you see
it I mean don't don't ruin my gig and
you see that mean so you got a it's
gonna take a lot of wisdom Peter good
luck yeah and and don't have something
about I mean yeah it is but but don't
mix them don't don't mix them don't
don't you know it's gonna be difficult
and you will get blamed the either way
okay get used to it we just talked about
the comments but obviously yeah and you
should know that this DCI has a separate
language for Buddhist principles we just
taught the teacher training in Sedona to
people from 27 countries and they call
the direct perception of emptiness
touching the diamond world and they're
not allowed to call it the direct
perception emptiness it's like that
there is a separate language but there
comes times when you're teaching a CI
when you might want to call it touching
the diamond world and and you know I
don't have any brilliant wisdom about it
but in general be aware that in a
country like argentina where DCI becomes
all yoga students it will fail and and
you won't you won't touch 3,000 4,000
people you will touch 20 yoga students
you see I mean so just be aware and you
know that you have to be adaptable and
you have to keep I believe you have to
keep them separate yeah yeah and it has
happened in some countries that the
businessmen left because the yoga showed
up you seen I mean and and we never
would have talked to the current
President of Argentina never would have
studied the pen with me if we had not
kept them separate you see how you do it
it's god bless I don't know but just be
aware of the issue and try to respect it
and do your best you it won't be perfect
there'll be failures then but we're
trying to in Russia in China in Dubai
we're struggling to not mention Buddhism
we're struggling not to be a Buddhist
organization because because not
everybody wants to be a Buddhist and
then you lose them you see I mean some
you gotta have two identities yeah and
it's uncomfortable to wear those tights
last question cuz these people won't go
home
I think the current thinking and it
might change is that and I think as
Hector's pointed out to me probably
we're gonna have to have a hybrid of in
person stuff and online stuff it ACI
teachers are not paid they will never
make money from a CI DCI teachers are
there on a track to make money so you
can't ask a CI teacher trainees to spend
ten thousand dollars a year to come to a
location which is what the DCI teacher
trainees do so it's gonna have to be
some kind of hybrid we're talking about
a point system maybe you get so many
points when I took a geology degree I
did much of it by correspondence there
was no internet at the time and but I
had to come to New York to do the lab
work in person and I got graded here in
person so that there was a in-person
element and there was a an online
element at the time how much I will
teach I'm booked for ten years
completely booked really honestly to the
half-hour I'm honestly I'm not
exaggerating I rarely exaggerate but I'm
born
I'm totally booked but me and Tim talked
about a way that I could teach men I
could teach much of the ACI courses
during a Diamond Mountain retreats twice
a year for teacher trainees and I'm
happy to do that and I and I think that
would be good but uh
but no it's fine
but uh but it's gonna be more you guys
then then it would have been ten years
ago because I you know people write me
emails guess I why didn't you answer my
email I have 67,000 unanswered emails
okay
and they said guess I just need 10
minutes your time yeah but there's
30,000 people who want 10 minutes it's
so three thirty thousand times ten it's
50,000 hours and I don't have it I can't
do it
and people say no geshe-la I'm your old
friend we used to hang out I said those
days are over you know I don't have five
minutes I don't have ten minutes you see
I can't answer every email so that's why
we're having a teacher training gee okay
it's a very lineage based it's passed
down and so it's it's different to me
than let's say a DC IT team or a yoga
routine or in which you can subscribe to
it and
and us or be admitted to it even if it's
an application base but the saw the
teachers in this lineage
they wear you
you have a relationship with your
teacher and it was passed down bad
information
by the grace of your teachers and the
blessings of your teachers with
just--how in which you can then teach
and it seems as though what what we're
talking about is institutionalizing
but then where does that relationship
with their teacher happened
quality control and
keeping you know a touch point was like
for me is when I have questions I still
mhm
and it's very special betting
relationship if we start to open it up
where does
it's a good question I'll give a couple
answers okay one is maybe we want to
allow a living room tract where someone
who took the course can still teach it
in their living room but they are not
our legal responsibility even in the
last year I have lost $50,000 on on
legal fees for teachers who did not
treat the students well and I'm not
interested in going there so we have to
have some kind of structure we have if
we decide to teach teachers we need we
need some kind of accountability to an
organization at the same time how can
you have guru yoga you know which is the
cornerstone of this whole tradition I
feel like like you will still have your
relationship with your personal teacher
and it will be passed down that way it's
like in the monastery the gesh a there's
a hybrid and then we'll stop because
it's getting late and and I know people
have to go there's a there's a hybrid
between the two things we have a gassy
course there's 60 students in my class
freshman class 60 guys started the first
year and that's institutionalized you
have to do certain exams you have to do
certain debates but your choice of
teacher is your personal thing and and
we I had 12 teachers and that until I
found my my my one you said I mean and
then we we we created a bond between
ourselves so I think it might work out
like that it'll be a hybrid and in the
monastery 60 guys have 12 different
teachers from which they are responsible
to learn the same basic information but
they create a different bond
with their teacher and that's fluid you
can switch you're allowed to switch
teachers if you find one that fits your
personality and you want to be devoted
to them you're allowed to switch to that
teachers classes and that's the way the
system goes in the monastery that way
all the geishas have a similar
qualifications but they still have guru
yoga they still have their personal
teacher so maybe it would be a hybrid
like that I think it's gonna work out
like that and I think it has to be that
way you can't have all guru yoga and you
can't have all institutionalized and I
think that's the compromise they make in
the monastery it's kind of cool
we all proceed roughly at the same speed
not always the same with our personal
gurus so we all have the same curriculum
roughly and then there's a process of
debate four or five hours that they
spent with students of a different guru
and then there's a bond created between
the students of different gurus and
that's also a beautiful thing and so I
think it's going to be those three
elements one there's an
institutionalized order at which you
have to go through the material to you
choose your guru and three the students
of different gurus exchange notes and
you learn a lot from urine from the
students of a different guru and what's
cool in that the background is you can
identify a guy's guru from its debating
like I've debated people from other
monasteries and I'll say your teachers
so and so on they say yeah and so there
is a bond and that bond lasts beyond the
Geshe course that lasts for life yeah or
in life's okay let's do a dedication
thank you good job it's a beautiful
place
I can't get out of the country without
going to New York that way good night
I'm sorry to keep you